<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on tomcohen.eth</title>
        <link>/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on tomcohen.eth</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>Yes</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2022 11:12:29 +0100</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Why I&#39;m not a Bitcoin Maximalist (anymore)</title>
            <link>/posts/bitcoin-maxi/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2022 11:12:29 +0100</pubDate>
            
            <guid>/posts/bitcoin-maxi/</guid>
            <description>This is something I&amp;rsquo;ve been putting off writing for a while now, but it had to happen. The Bitcoin community gave me so much over the years, and I hope this will serve as a small nudge to making it as incredible as it used to. For years I was &amp;ldquo;the bitcoin person&amp;rdquo; in pretty much any group I was in. Bitcoin, not crypto. And for the past few months, I&amp;rsquo;ve slowly distanced myself from that label.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is something I&rsquo;ve been putting off writing for a while now, but it had to happen. The Bitcoin community gave me so much over the years, and I hope this will serve as a small nudge to making it as incredible as it used to. For years I was &ldquo;the bitcoin person&rdquo; in pretty much any group I was in. Bitcoin, not crypto. And for the past few months, I&rsquo;ve slowly distanced myself from that label. This is why.</p>
<h2 id="finding-bitcoin-and-becoming-a-maximalist">Finding Bitcoin and Becoming a Maximalist</h2>
<p>Then, a little over a decade ago, I stumbled onto Bitcoin. I was supposed to give a small presentation to my team about asymmetric encryption and while I was googling for interesting applications I could use as examples, I came across an article decribing a system that used common cryptographic primitives to do something amazing - building magic internet money. It felt exactly like what the hacker culture I grew up on was always supposed to build. A completely decentralized network of computers running open source software that could securely transfer value between each other, without the need for any kind of intermediaries. It was uncensorable, unstoppable, and completely unlike anything I&rsquo;ve seen before. I was hooked pretty much instantly.</p>
<p>The roots of my maximalist go back to the altcoin boom of 2013-2014. There was suddenly an explosion of new cryptocurrencies; and while many of them were silly forks of bitcoin with a simple parameter change, some were actually trying to build something better. But Bitcoin was consistently the better bet. It had the best devs, the largest network effects, and most importantly - it had a community that was by far the most directionally aligned with the vision of building a truly decentralised consensus system.</p>
<p>The blocksize war is where this truly seemed to shine. While the Bitcoin network was clogging and fees soared, the community waged the closest thing it ever had to a civil war. The people who cared less about decentralisation tried to push naive scaling solutions that would hurt decentralisation in the long term, and special interest groups tried to leverage the pain of costs to increase their hold over the network. Those efforts failed, and the side that won was the side that was willing to endure short-term pain and adopt the solution that wasn&rsquo;t the simplest to understand but the one that&rsquo;s healthier for Bitcoin in the long term. The community members that weren&rsquo;t happy with this hard-forked themselves into oblivion.</p>
<p>At the same time, Bitcoin&rsquo;s largest competitor Ethereum was having a moment of its own. The DAO hack happened, and the community did something that to this day I consider Ethereum&rsquo;s greatest sin - they hard-forked to change the balance of accounts on a live chain. This is something that was so far removed from what I considered a healthy community behaviour that for years to come I couldn&rsquo;t take anything that happened on Ethereum seriously.</p>
<p>As the years went by, most of the arguments against Bitcoin I kept running into were bad. Arguments about energy consumption that were full of special pleading, arguments about scaling that didn&rsquo;t take layer2 into account, and arguments about volatility or value that were coming from a place of western financial privilege. The more I ran into those arguments, the more I was sure Bitcoin is the way. There was just no real competition.</p>
<h2 id="pow-pos-and-maximalism-cracks">PoW, PoS, and maximalism cracks</h2>
<p>About a year ago, when we were on the high side of our regularly scheduled four-year hype cycle, I found myself having quite a few conversations about PoW vs PoS - mostly in defence of PoW. People were raving about how Ethereum is about to move to PoS, and how energy efficient it was, and how Bitcoin is outdated because of it. The Pro-PoS crowd always glanced over (or just completely ignored) the new trust assumptions baked into the system and quickly started applying the heuristic learnt over the past decade - Bitcoin is just prioritising the correct long-term decentralisation over short-term wins. After quite a few of those discussions, it seemed I should sit down and just write a comparison of the two systems, using the best arguments for and against each side I could possibly find. And then I started to notice something that made me really uneasy: the bitcoin community was making a lot of really bad arguments.</p>
<p>No one was really talking about the trust assumptions and the increased reliance on social coordination. Instead, there were a lot of incorrect claims about stakers being able to change consensus in a way miners can&rsquo;t, red herring claims about Ethereum requiring stronger hardware to run a node (which isn&rsquo;t relevant to PoW vs PoS), weird arguments about the energy consumption from mining actually being good for the environment (?)&hellip; And for months I just kept digging while my brain slowly grew to accept something it didn&rsquo;t want to: the bitcoin community is just not the one making the best arguments anymore. There&rsquo;s probably no better example of this than the Bankless episode from the end of March titled &ldquo;The PoW vs. PoS Debate&rdquo;. This was one of the most confusing and bizarre discussions I&rsquo;ve ever seen. Justin, arguing for PoS, spent the 90 minute debate consistently making to-the-point, logically consistent, <em>relevant</em> arguments that addressed the differences between PoW and PoS. Lyn, arguing for PoW, spent the time mostly making this discussion a weird semantics game about commodities and securities which was both not really logically coherent and consistently shifted the discussion to Bitcoin and Ethereum instead of the underlying consensus mechanisms. The worst part was that everyone in the Bitcoin community thought this was a ridiculously good performance on Lyn&rsquo;s side.</p>
<p>While logically I could see that the Ethereum community was now consistently making better arguments, it still took a while for me to accept it. It was still the project that hardforked to change the balance of actors they didn&rsquo;t like, and it was still a place where a lot of pseudo-decentralisation ran supreme with over-reliance on centralised node providers. But as I started looking more into Ethereum, I also started picking up on the fact that it&rsquo;s a place where a lot of the most interesting things are happening. The community is vibrant and welcoming, they&rsquo;re not just building cool things but also thinking about how those things affect people and society. There is a lot of effort put into building collective systems and making sure everyone wins. And most importantly, it has the community that is most directionally aligned with the vision of building a truly decentralised consensus system.</p>
<p>I want to stress that I&rsquo;m not making any sort of definitive statement here. It is still very possible that Ethereum&rsquo;s community would choose a path that would be harmful to decentralisation in the long term, and while the community is in a better place than it was a few years ago, there are still a lot of bad actors. But I think it&rsquo;s fairly clear that the majority of the community is on the same side as Bitcoin&rsquo;s original vision.</p>
<h2 id="bitcoin-as-a-community">Bitcoin as a community</h2>
<p>I think the most disappointing thing about the current situation of Bitcoin is the community. The community used to be a place where the most interesting ideas were being debated in a respectful manner; now it&rsquo;s a place where the same talking points are being repeated over and over again. A place where ideas are not being debated, but dismissed out of hand. A place of tribalism and echo chambers. A place where people are not just wrong but bad. The community used to be filled with bright and interesting people, now it&rsquo;s mostly filled with trolls, scammers, and grifters.</p>
<p>At the worst end, there&rsquo;s now a significant portion of the community treating the Bitcoin code and Satoshi in a quasi-religious manner - as if the whitepaper was perfect scripture that wasn&rsquo;t meant to grow and be iterated on but instead was a singular stroke of genius of a mysterious demi-god that cannot be improved except in small soft-forks and layer2. This is the single most dangerous meme in the community right now, and it&rsquo;s something that needs to be actively fought against.</p>
<p>In the middle, there are a lot of people that seem to have completely given up on the vision of Bitcoin as a global decentralised consensus system that can serve anyone anywhere in the world, and are instead treating it like a small club for rich guys in the western world. They talk about Bitcoin as a store of value that needs to stay as volatile as possible and as a commodity that needs to be hoarded and not spent. They talk about how Bitcoin is purely a tool for making money, and anything that affects the price in a negative way should be actively fought against.</p>
<p>And then there are a lot of people that are still fighting the good fight. People who understand and actively work on the trade-offs that need to be made between decentralisation, security, and usability. People who care about scaling and accessible layer2 solutions. People who think about how we can make the network secure for everyone, not just rich people. People who want to build a better future for everyone, not just themselves. They&rsquo;re still here, but as time goes on they too are growing tired of the toxicity and constant in-fighting. Many, like me, grow disillusioned with Bitcoin and slowly start moving out.</p>
<h1 id="the-road-ahead">The road ahead</h1>
<p>I&rsquo;m not sure where Bitcoin will end up. It&rsquo;s possible that the current tensions will calm down and we&rsquo;ll start to rebuild the community that once was. And it&rsquo;s also possible that the community will continue to move in the same direction, and Bitcoin will slowly become an irrelevant relic of the past. Personally, I&rsquo;m still very much in love with the idea of Bitcoin and a decentralised consensus system. I&rsquo;m just no longer sure that Bitcoin is the best implementation. The beauty of this beast is that no matter if I&rsquo;m right or not - we&rsquo;re still going to decentralise the world.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s to building the future.</p>
<p>T</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
